Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adopted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For all the lovers in the world,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For all the lovers in the world,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
(Noble Lady Sourire)
Is the name tag for Lady Sourire ready?
Yes, do we put it in tonight?
His Majesty didn't say anything.
Keep it here.
Lady Sourire is His Majesty's new favorite.
Her name tag will be used a lot.
The apple tree bears flower for the candlelight at night.
Also because His Majesty balances the Yin-Yang in our palace.
Peace to Lady Sourire.
Congratulations, My Lady.
His Majesty invites you to the Hot Spring Palace.
Madam Cui can go with you.
I thank His Majesty.
Please get ready for the trip.
The carriage will leave after lunch.
Yes, I will get everything ready for My Lady.
Allow me to go back to work.
Where is the Hot Spring Palace?
Why are you going by carriage?
It's the palace in Changping [now a district of Beijing].
His Majesty must be giving you a getaway.
Hot spring is good for your health, My Lady.
Your Majesty.
Is everything ready?
When will His Majesty leave?
We will leave after lunch.
Su Peisheng said Lady Sourire is going with us too.
Autumn, tell His Majesty that I'm feeling unwell.
I'm not able to go with him.
Your Majesty will be using the Gold Phoenix Pool
while Lady Sourire will use the Blue Phoenix Pool.
She won't disturb you.
I'm just doing His Majesty a favor.
That is very kind of Your Majesty.
I can't imagine what would happen
were Consort Fleur going with her.
Is it the Emperor Cheng of Han?
[who liked to watch his concubines bathe]
I'm not Zhao Hede [the empress of Emperor Cheng].
Don't you dare compare me to Emperor Cheng of Han.
He's not a sagacious emperor like you.
I love your flattery.
But how could you tell that I'm a sagacious emperor?
Don't judge me.
I know nothing about the state affairs.
But your concubines are prettier than Emperor Cheng's,
and more virtuous in character.
He is not as lucky as you are.
Lady Sourire has the gift of the gab.
She isn't just a pretty face.
I am luckier than Emperor Cheng.
Are you scared?
Not at all.
You don't even look at me.
Concubines are always scared
when they serve in bed for the first time.
I'm not scared.
While I'm just a concubine to you,
I see you as my husband.
And this is my wedding night.
I'm simply nervous.
That is okay.
The etiquette instructor must have told you what to do.
I'm nervous because I was simply instructed how to serve an emperor.
I do not know how I should serve my husband.
I meant no offence to Your Majesty.
All my concubines served me in awe.
Even the Empress was meticulously careful.
No one ever said anything like that to me.
If you see me as your husband,
you can relax when you're with me.
Your Highness had back pain in the morning.
Please go sleep early.
She is finally serving His Majesty.
After a long time. It's not a big deal.
He upgraded her as an exception,
visits her every two days,
and took her to the Hot Spring Palace.
He only took her with him.
Is she the next Yang Guifei?
[the favorite consort of Emperor Xuanzong of Tang]
Yang Guifei ended up with a tragic death.
His Majesty acts on impulse.
Escort Yu was forgotten in no time
even if she was in her prime.
I hope so.
No one ever knows His Majesty.
What are you doing?
I'm sorry to have awaken you.
It was the flickering candlelight.
I was glad to see the candles were burning bright.
Why is that?
In a traditional wedding, they burn two candles all night
so that the newly-weds can grow grey and old together.
They use red candles carved with phoenix, however.
We have to make do with what we have.
I'm over 40 years old.
I will have to live to 100 years old
if you are to grow grey and old with me.
An emperor lives for ten thousand years.
It is unfair to make you die at 100
if you are to grow grey and old with me.
You're calculating.
Do you think I'm silly for believing in the candlelight?
You have the heart of a child.
It's adorable.
In my life,
there was once I had red candles burning all night.
Wasn't there twice?
I did not have a nuptial chamber with the step empress.
Do you really want to grow old with me?
Every girl in this world wishes to grow old with their husband.
I am just an ordinary girl.
But I'm afraid that is my wishful thinking.
What I need in a palace is just an ordinary girl.
I'll see you as the jewel in the crown.
I won't let you down.
(tut) Don't cry.
I need pen and paper.
For what?
To write that down in case you renege on the promise.
You're such a child.
An emperor's words carry weight.
You should sleep now.
You need to rise early tomorrow.
I’m not sleeping without you.
Peace to My Lady.
- Lingrong
- Peace to Lady Shen.
You're so early.
I was going to pay respect to Her Majesty,
but she's feeling unwell today.
So I made my way here.
You have bags under your eyes.
Did you not sleep well last night?
I was staying up talking to Concubine Estime.
Sourire stayed at the Hot Spring Palace last night.
She must have served His Majesty.
Of course.
I must be the first concubine ever
who was sent out of the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
Let bygones be bygones.
You'll have another chance.
Another chance ...
I'm not as lucky as you two.
I'll go congratulate Sourire when she's back.
I kneel and bow to Your Majesty.
Autumn, help Lady Sourire up.
- I thank Your Majesty.
- My Lady.
Have a seat.
It must be a lot of trouble for you to greet me this way
when you have just recovered and returned to the palace.
But it's required that a concubine
must greet the Empress after serving His Majesty.
I should have done it the day after I served His Majesty.
I apologize for the delay.
It is important to follow the rules,
but more so to follow them in an expedient manner.
I am pleased as long as His Majesty is.
Don't let the rules rule you.
Your Majesty is kind and caring.
The palace is graced as peace is with Your Majesty.
That's very sweet of you.
No wonder His Majesty is fond of you.
You are pretty and smart. It shouldn't take so long
for you to get to where you are today.
Good things come to those who wait.
You are welcome to my palace anytime you like.
Just feel at home.
Sure.
I really like the fragrance of the fruits here.
It calms me down.
I don't like burning incense, or using rouge and powder.
So I have fresh fruits sent here every day.
I learned a lot.
My Lady, Her Majesty had intended to visit you
time and again while you were sick.
But the doctors suggested that you stay quarantined.
Her Majesty wasn't able to go.
Her Majesty thinks of you a lot.
I thank Your Majesty.
We held the Selection last year for His Majesty
to have more concubines to his liking.
Your priority is to regain good health for His Majesty.
I will follow Your Majesty's advice.
I enjoy talking to you,
and couldn't help getting in a talkative mood.
You should go get some rest.
Autumn, please walk her out.
Good for you, My Lady.
- My Lady.
- Xiao-Yunzi.
Why are you here?
I wish to congratulate My Lady.
He came all the way to get rewarded.
My Lady will reward you later.
Madam, you misunderstood me.
My Lady, I was instructed to tell you not to return right away.
Why is that?
You'll find out later. Please take a walk in the garden.
All right.
Your Highness, my stomach hurts.
Go.
I find it unpleasant that Kang Luhai has a sneaking habit.
He worked for Consort Honnête.
I wouldn't employ him otherwise.
You have a big heart.
I would never trust a betrayer.
What a nice garden!
The flowers here are the most beautiful.
I bow to Lady Sourire.
Peace and Grace to My Lady.
It's Kang Luhai.
Kang Luhai.
Thank you for remembering me.
What brought you here so early in the morning.
Concubine Beauté and Lady Cao
are paying respect to Her Majesty.
I was waiting here for you, My Lady.
Does Concubine Beauté have a message for me?
No, I'm not here for Concubine Beauté.
I'm here to ask you for a favor, My Lady.
Go ahead.
I've been wishing to congratulate you.
But I couldn't get away from work,
and His Majesty restricted visitors to you palace.
I waited anxiously all these days,
hoping to see you, My Lady.
I'm ill at ease if I cannot congratulate you in person.
Please get to the point.
If you do not disdain, I will work for you at all costs.
That is very kind of you.
But does Concubine Beauté know?
Hmm,
She might be unhappy if she knows.
I'm ranked at Noble Lady.
I cannot make such a request to a Concubine.
Don't worry, My Lady.
No one in the palace would go against your wish.
All you have to do is ask.
Did your stomach hurt because you saw your former mistress?
Peace and grace to Concubine Beauté.
Peace and grace to Lady Cao.
You shouldn't have.
We are at the same rank.
You know her rank,
but she doesn't.
I understand that His Majesty
had new servants sent to your palace.
Are they not enough so that
you wish to re-employ my incompetent eunuch?
Your Highness misunderstood.
I am grateful that Kang Luhai can work for you.
Any request to re-employ him for me is out of line.
I am aware of the protocol in the palace.
Lady Sourire is very well-mannered.
It's not surprising that His Majesty likes you so much
that I cannot compare with.
His Majesty pities me for being unwell,
but Your Highness holds a place
in his heart hundreds of times higher.
Stupid eunuch!
Slap yourself for offending Her Highness.
(My offence deserves death)
Beauté, don't be upset over a eunuch.
It's not worth it.
(My offence deserves death)
"The monkeys would want
four acorns next time if you give them three."
It's even worse when the monkey is castrated.
He looks down his nose at me
while sucking the boots of hers,
not even remembering how he begged me
to dig him out of the tomb of a living dead.
Now he eats with his eyes on someone else's plate.
Beauté, don't waste your breath even if you're mad.
Sorry that you had to hear my angry talk to my servant.
Your Highness is free to punish your servant,
regardless of what you say or do to him.
But many eyes are watching us in the garden.
Your Highness might as well do this later in your palace.
Enough.
I need to pay respect to the Empress.
You're good to go.
I thank Your Highness.
Thank you for saving my life (X2)
You are smart.
Concubine Beauté wouldn't let me off without your intercession.
She might not forgive you.
Good luck.
They hold a grudge against you, My Lady.
Shame on him.
Even the maid could scold Kang Luhai.
He must be having a hard time working there.
Loyalty is everything for a servant.
No one would ever trust a flip-flopper again.
It serves him right.
But Concubine Beauté wasn't nice to talk to.
I feel aggrieved for you.
I like her straightforward personality.
My Lady, congratulations on
being awarded a pepper-painted room!
This is the highest honor!
The highest honor!
Congratulations, My Lady!
Come on in, My Lady!
Our palace looks fantastic!
What is smelling so good?
It's the walls, My Lady.
We were in a hurry to decorate your room
at His Majesty’s behest.
I hope you like it, My Lady.
The pepper-painted room is a wedding custom,
wishing for a warm and prolific life.
It is awarded to the Empress but rarely the concubines.
The only other awardee was Consort Fleur.
- Congratulations, My Lady.
- Congratulations!
Please go inside, My Lady.
If you would like to have a look at your bed.
Is this the custom for a concubine's first-time service?
Thank you for your hard work.
It is the custom, but it goes deeper underneath.
[peanuts, dried dates, dried dragon eyes, and copper coins]
His Majesty took my words to heart.
His Majesty learned about bed decoration in folk marriage.
He apologized for not having it ready at the Hot Spring Palace.
The time is always right for a surprise like this.
All right, My Lady should get some rest.
Vermilion and Jade will stay to serve her.
This is terrific, My Lady!
Your parents will be so glad.
His Majesty hold you dear to his heart, My Lady.
It's such a relief after all these months.
There are yet many more months to come.
Every month will be just as good, My Lady.
The other concubines were carried to serve His Majesty.
But you were carried in a wagon.
Don't make fun of me.
I'm not. I'm happy for you.
But not every concubine would feel the same way.
They can't go a day without being jealous.
Concubine Beauté is an outspoken person.
It's better to have an open enemy than a false friend.
I agree.
But she has Consort Fleur at her back,
who is alarmed by another pepper-painted room in the palace.
I never expected His Majesty to treat me so nicely.
Everything went far beyond what's ever possible.
Meizhuang, is this even real?
Of course it is. His love is burning red.
His love is real.
Concubine Beauté's bitterness is real.
And the ongoing rivalries in the palace.
Meizhuang, what should I do?
Endure it.
Endure it?
The Empress is not even able to balance with Consort Fleur,
let alone us.
We have nothing to compare with
the place she holds and her family background.
We are striking a stone with eggs to compete with her.
We'll have to wait with patience.
Point well taken.
But will you be annoyed?
I was expecting this day when you were selected.
I feel hopeful as long as you are in a good place.
I'm not annoyed but envious of my sister.
But do you feel upset?
A little bit.
But the palace is never short of beloved concubines:
Consort Fleur, yourself, and someone else in the future.
Life is too short to be upset by you guys.
Another full moon.
I hope everythiny's fine at home.
Do you miss home, My Lady?
All the time when I feel alone in the palace.
But you're not alone here, My Lady.
Lady Sourire and Lady Shen are like sisters to you.
You should visit them oftener.
Especially Lady Sourire,
you might even see His Majesty at her palace.
No, I shouldn't steal her spotlight.
Don't overthink, My Lady.
Lady Sourire is always generous to you.
She had two pieces of satin sent to you today.
That was her being kind.
Even the closest friends have some distance between them.
Meizhuang is the best friend of Sourire,
but she could not sleep when Sourire served His Majesty.
My Lady, Mr Xu from Attendance Services.
Peace to My Lady.
Why did you make the trip yourself, sir?
My Lady, His Majesty instructed me to inform you
that you will stay at his residence tonight.
Thank you, sir.
I bid you goodnight.
You were just back from the Hot Spring Palace.
His Majesty can't get enough of you.
Stop it.
My Lady, His Majesty is finishing up work.
He'll be with you shortly.
Please wait here.
Do I need to get changed?
His Majesty said that you'll just need to wait.
Thank you, Madam.
Your Majesty.
You must be hungry.
I got snacks for you.
There's only one serving.
Your Majesty will eat first.
I had some earlier.
Give it a try and see if you like it.
Thank you.
It's raw.
As you requested.
[生(raw) also means to have a baby]
Lady Sourire is cute when she is mad.
You played a trick on me.
All right, all right,
It wasn't a trick.
It was supposed to be served at the Hot Spring Palace.
It's one of the customs in folk wedding.
But we aren't allowed to follow the customs in the palace.
I will do everything possible for you.
You're so good to me.
I remember seeing you in the shadows of the apricot flowers.
You looked detached from all the chaos in the palace.
I felt like it was just you and me in this world.
I'm flattered.
There are many talented beauties in the palace.
I am nobody compared to them.
You are Zhen Huan.
You don't compare them to yourself.
You are perfect being who you are.
She covets my servant when she's just a Noble Lady.
I can't even imagine what she will be.
You can't blame her for the disloyalty of your servant.
But you have only yourself to blame for your short temper.
You should try to be composed like Lady Cao.
My eyes tolerate no grain of sand.
She'll be up herself when His Majesty likes her.
And soon His Majesty will stop liking her.
If you remember Yu.
Lady Sourire isn't bold like her.
She showed a lot of respect for you.
But you lost your temper at her courtesy.
That is inappropriate.
She's just new to the job.
New to the job?
But she has a pepper-painted room like Your Highness.
And His Majesty visits her 8 out of 10 times this month.
You aren't mute when you don't talk.
Your Highness, quiet dogs bite.
You're a quarter earlier than yesterday.
I was hope the night would fall faster.
We just played Go in the afternoon before I went back for dinner.
A day feels like three years without seeing you.
A dinner felt like a year.
Lady Sourire served the night before last,
and yesterday,
and played Go with His Majesty this afternoon.
And serving tonight.
What a minx!
What witchcraft did she spell on His Majesty?
If only witchcraft works for some of us.
Even Yu was better than her.
(Record of Attendance)
(name on the doll: Zhen Huan)
Bitch
Go to hell.
Go to hell, bitch.
I bow in respect before Your Majesty.
I beg your pardon for my delay.
It's okay.
You are young and need more sleep.
I thank Your Majesty.
I bow in respect before Your Highnesses.
Rise.
I was hoping to have gifts sent to you for your service.
The lamas made a tribute payment with
consecrated swastika(卍) blankets.
I kept one for you.
It will bring good luck for having a child.
Thank Your Majesty so much.
Good for you.
You'll be the next Consort Astuce when you have a child.
Consort Astuce is much more blessed
than the mother of the Fourth Prince.
She couldn't even look at her son before ...
Why did you bring up his mother?
Don't you gossip about a prince!
The gossip ends here in my palace.
His Majesty will be upset if he hears it.
Concubine Beauté, we don't talk about people that bring bad luck.
All right, you can leave now.
I'm going to visit the Empress Dowager.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
Why would you upset Her Majesty?
She minds her own business.
Why would you care?
Who is the mother of the Fourth Prince?
Why would Her Majesty be so upset?
I don't really know.
But I heard his mother is an ugly maid.
That's why His Majesty doesn't like the Fourth Prince
and keeps him in the Summer Palace.
Why would His Majesty sleep with an ugly maid?
Be quiet.
It happened when His Majesty was drunk.
The prior emperor was furious about it.
The incident had a negative effect on his accession to the throne.
Never mention it to anyone.
Thank you.
I bow in respect before Consort Fleur.
I bow in respect before Concubine Beauté.
- Rise
- Thank you.
Lady Sourire was always on time to pay respect to Her Majesty.
What happened today?
I regret my indolence.
It's not a matter of indolence.
You didn't get enough sleep for serving His Majesty too much.
Your Highness understands that
we should talk about His Majesty appropriately.
I hope Your Highness would not mind me for speaking frankly.
And I would appreciate any advice from Your Highness.
Lady Sourire has been rather busy lately.
I wonder if Lady Shen would like
to make a copy of Analects for Women.
It will remind women in the harem of good manners.
With great pleasure, Your Highness.
May I ask when it is expected?
Take your time.
I will have it picked up when I need it.
It seems that Lady Shen lost a few pounds.
Is that because His Majesty hasn't been visiting you?
Thank Your Highness for noticing.
It's just that the heat spoils my appetite.
Oh, I see.
I thought it was because you were
upset by Lady Sourire's advancement.
I dare not.
It's not surprising that Lady Sourire
wins a place in His Majesty's affection.
But you two are like sisters to each other.
Sisters share.
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
The falling leaves from the phoenix tree.